<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ar-style1.xsl"?>
<!--DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"--><ead relatedencoding="MARC21"> 
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"> 
	 <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="VVK">ARA-0002</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <!--TITLE OF FINDING AID-->
		  <titleproper>American Ophthalmological Society Records</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>1864-2012</subtitle> 
		  <author>Collection processed and described by Rebecca Pou. Updated 2012.</author>
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt>
            <date>2008</date>
		</publicationstmt>
		<notestmt><note><p>Preliminary processing and description done by Donald Prochera, 2007.</p></note></notestmt>
	 </filedesc> 
<profiledesc>
  <creation>Finding aid encoded by Rebecca Pou, <date normal="20081119">November 19, 2008.</date></creation>
  </profiledesc>	 
		<revisiondesc>
			<change>Finding aid updated to reflect addition of Minutes of the Council, 1993-2012. Materials sent to NYAM by Stephen Moss, <date normal="20120701">September 2012</date></change>
		</revisiondesc>
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="collection"> 
	 <did> 
		<head>Collection Summary</head> 
		<origination> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="110">American Ophthalmological Society</corpname> </origination>	
		<!-- UNITTITLE HERE = TITLE OF COLLECTION -->
		<unittitle encodinganalog="245">American Ophthalmological Society Records</unittitle> 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1864-2012</unitdate> 
		<physdesc> <extent encodinganalog="300">1.4 linear foot</extent>; <extent encodinganalog="300">2 boxes</extent>	
		  </physdesc> 
		<unitid>Mss.arc</unitid> 
		<repository encodinganalog="852"> 
		  <corpname>New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.</corpname> </repository> 
	 </did> 
	 <prefercite encodinganalog="524"> 
		<head>Preferred Citation</head> 
		<p>American Ophthalmological Society Records. Rare Book Room, New York Academy of Medicine Library.</p> 
	 </prefercite> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="545"> 
		<head>Historical Note</head> 
		<p>Founded in 1864, the mission of the American Ophthalmological Society has been "to promote excellence in patient care, education and research, to address essential issues in medicine, and to advance the art and science of ophthalmology." As the oldest American specialty medical society, AOS upholds traditions of peer-reviewed independent research and scientific exchange. Meetings for Society business, lectures and discussion of ophthalmological practice and education have traditionally been held whenever possible in various cities and towns through the country, reflecting the growth of the AOS membership.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> 
		<head>Scope and Content</head> 
		<p>Deposit includes a constitution and signature book, minutes of the American Ophthalmological Society, minutes of the Society's Council, and a copy of <title render="italic">The American Ophthalmological Society 1864-1989: a Continuation of Wheeler's First Hundred Years</title> by Frank W. Newell.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	<arrangement>
		<head>Arrangement of Collection</head>
		<p>Most of the records are in bound volumes and chronological order has been maintained: Signature Book, 1864-1988; Minutes of the American Ophthalmological Society, 1864-1901 and 1902-1916; Minutes of the Council of the American Ophthalmological Society, 1924-1942, 1942-1974, 1975-1992, and 1993-2012 (last set of minutes are in folders); and <title render="italic">The American Ophthalmological Society 1864-1989: a Continuation of Wheeler's First Hundred Years</title> by Frank W. Newell (1989). 
</p>
	</arrangement>	  
	 <controlaccess> 
		<head>Index Terms</head> 
		<p>This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog
		  of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials
		  about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these
		  headings.</p> 
		<controlaccess> 
			<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnap">American Ophthalmological Society.</corpname> 
			<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Medicine -- United States -- Societies, etc.</subject> 		  
		  	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Ophthalmology -- United States -- Societies, etc.</subject> 
		</controlaccess> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <userestrict encodinganalog="540"> 
		<p>Available to those bearing a letter of permission from an officer of the Society.</p>
		<p>Requests for permission to quote from or publish any materials should
		  be directed to the curatorial staff of the Rare Book Room in writing.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <acqinfo encodinganalog="541"> 
		<head>Provenance</head> 
		<p>On deposit by the American Ophthalmological Society.</p>
	 </acqinfo> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>