<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ar-style1.xsl"?>
<!--DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"--><ead relatedencoding="MARC21"> 
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"> 
	 <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="VVK">ARM-0008</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <!--TITLE OF FINDING AID-->
		  <titleproper>Meyer M. Melicow Collection</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>1927-1983</subtitle> 
		 <author>Collection processed and described by Donald Corr</author>
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt>
            <date>2013</date>
		</publicationstmt>
	 </filedesc> 
<profiledesc>
  <creation>Finding aid encoded by Donald Corr, <date normal="20130509">May 9, 2013.</date></creation>
  </profiledesc>	 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="collection"> 
	 <did> 
		<head>Collection Summary</head> 
		<origination> 
		  <persname encodinganalog="100">Meyer M. Melicow</persname> </origination>
		<!-- UNITTITLE HERE = TITLE OF COLLECTION -->
		<unittitle encodinganalog="245">Meyer M. Melicow Collection</unittitle> 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1927-1983</unitdate> 
		<physdesc> <extent encodinganalog="300">2.5 linear feet</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<unitid>Mss.arc</unitid> 
		<repository encodinganalog="852"> 
		  <corpname>New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.</corpname> </repository> 
	 </did> 
	 <prefercite encodinganalog="524"> 
		<head>Preferred Citation</head> 
		<p>Meyer M. Melicow Collection. Rare Book Room, New York Academy of Medicine.</p> 
	 </prefercite> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="545"> 
	 <head>Historical Statement</head>
		<p>Meyer M. Melicow (1894-1983) was a faculty member at Columbia University’s College of Physicians and Surgeons and author of more than 200 papers on pioneering research about urological disease. Melicow was also a published visual artist who regularly contributed artwork to the New York Physicians’ Art Association’s annual exhibition, frequently held at the New York Academy of Medicine.</p>
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> 
		<head>Scope and Content</head> 
		<p>The collection consists of Dr. Melicow’s papers in addition to records of the New York Physicians’ Art Association. The papers include clippings about the representation of medicine in art, bound volumes of Physicians and Surgeons Quarterly (Melicow frequently selected and described the covers), and articles written and compiled by him on urological disease. Minutes of the Committee on the Library at the New York Academy of Medicine, of which Melicow was a member, are also present.</p>
		<p>Records of the New York Physicians’ Art Association include three bound volumes, one containing Dr. Melicow’s reviews of exhibitions published in <emph render="italic">The New York Physician</emph> and two containing exhibition catalogs. A volume containing exhibition programs and newsletters from the American Physician’s Art Association is also present.  
</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 	  
	 <controlaccess> 
		<head>Index Terms</head> 
		<p>This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog
		  of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials
		  about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these
		  headings.</p> 
		<controlaccess>  
		  <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Exhibitions</subject>
		  <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Medicine and art</subject>	
		  <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Urologists -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>		 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Physicians -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.</subject>		 
		  <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Melicow, Meyer M.</persname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcnaf">American Physicians' Art Association</corpname>
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcnaf">New York Physicians' Art Assocation</corpname>
		</controlaccess> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <arrangement>
	 <head>Arrangement of Collection</head>
		<p>Collection arranged in two series. Series 1, the Melicow Papers, consists of 39 loose folders and six bound volumes. Series 2, the New York Physician Art Association Records, consists of four bound volumes.</p>
	 </arrangement>
	 <userestrict encodinganalog="540"> 
		<p>Requests for permission to quote from or publish any materials should
		  be directed to the curatorial staff of the Rare Book Room in writing.</p> 
	 </userestrict>
 </archdesc>
</ead>